five times fittest man on Earth Matt
Frasier said it best he said if every
athlete could just take a pill for sleep
and water everyone would take it because
it would feel like cheating protein you
really got to prioritize and if you
start with protein if you base every
meal around quality protein other things
start to fall into place you can push
you can pull you can Squat and you can
hip hinge doing movements that
encapsulate all four of those movements
it's really helpful to be like okay
that's a full
workout happy New Year and welcome to
strength weekly the weekly show that
keeps you updated on everything from
around the barbell game we are doing
things a little differently to kick off
2024 with literally the only Fitness
resolutions that matter we are
highlighting three things that are going
to help you achieve whatever goal you
set out to achieve first off how body
weight training can help anyone yes
literally anyone stay on track with
their Fitness and strength goals we're
also going to talk about really the only
Mac macronutrient counting that everyone
needs to do I hate counting macros this
is the only thing I do it's kind of been
lifechanging and I'm not pulling my
punch on that and third we're talking
about how to get the best sleep of your
life which is important for
every athlete weekend warrior to the
absolute Elite but before we get to that
I want to say
subscribe to barbend on YouTube because
we're going to be back next week with
all the news from around the strength
world heavy deadlifts clean jerks
snatches maybe a few competition wins
and World Records who knows it's going
to be a crazy Year Phil what are you
looking forward to most in
2024 and why is it Valentine's Day so
it's Valentine's Day because by then I
should have exquisitely crafted visible
abs and I'm very excited to finally have
that achieved after making that New
Year's resolution every time for the
last 20 years sometimes the ABS Hide
Under The Bushel I know I've been hiding
mine for years years I do want to say a
quick disclaimer I'm going to read this
for btim so the lawyers don't get mad at
me hey folks the content on barbend
including strength weekly is meant to be
informative in nature but it shouldn't
take the place of advice Andor
supervision from from a medical
professional the opinions articles and
videos from this media property are not
intended for uses diagnosis prevention
Andor treatment of health problems speak
with your physician if you have any
any concerns Phil why do you think some
people in the barbell game scoff when
they hear body weight
training I think there's something about
not being able to pack on some loads for
added resistance when we know that
resistance training is what usually or
is what is proven to uh add gains but uh
just because you don't have a barbell or
some weight plates doesn't mean that you
can't get those same benefits if you
just do the work just got to do the work
body weight training is useful for any
type of athlete and I think what's
really interesting is when I talk to
athletes at top of their game in Elite
strength sports power lifting
weightlifting Etc they do more body
weight training the longer they're in
the game and the more experience they
get under their proverbial belts Than
People necessarily anticipate and than a
lot of people think and I think that's
because they see the benefit of mixing
up the type of resistance training and
also just the nice hypertrophic
bulletproofing your body effect that
basic body weight training can have for
a number of reps acred across the months
and years why don't we go back and forth
with some of the reasons we really like
body weight training mine I'll start off
I'll kick things off I love kicking
things off for I'm selfish body weight
training eliminates excuses not to train
if I'm on the road or my schedule is
crazy at home and I can't make it to the
gym body weight training allows me to
get in some resistance training to get
some load
in a very short period of time with
basically zero excuses and one of my
favorite things to do is if I have just
missed my training session because life
got in the way I will make sure that I
acrew and this is just me personally I
will acrew 120 push-ups and 120 squats
just body weight squats right and I feel
like I've done something and I've given
my body a stimulus that it responds to
one of my favorite things to do to add a
cardio component I just set a running
clock and I do sets 10 and 10 10
push-ups 10 squats 10 push-ups 10 squats
go to I get 120 of those partition
however you want maybe it's five and
five whatever it is right one of my
favorite no excuse things takes me under
15 minutes and it's like cool I worked
out today I did something today it's
better than nothing even if I missed a
training session even if I'm traveling
even if I'm busy there's basically no
excuse for me not to do it Phil what's
one of your benefits so what you just
said is what typically I run into as
well if I'm ever on the road it's really
nice that you can just use body weight
literally wherever you are I also find
that because body weight feels easier
when you're first starting it uh has a
sense of almost feeling passive so like
if I'm listening to a podcast or I have
something going on in front of me that's
like sort of a distraction if your
mechanics are solid enough like if you
have a solid body weight Squat and you
know it's just like you you move through
the motions you know it's nice to be
able to like not feel like okay I'm Max
I'm going to my one rep max and that's
going to be difficult and I have to put
all my focus on it you can really get
through a body weight workout in a way
that I find to be uh a bit more casual
while still going to failure so I'm in
your similar in your space rather than
partitioning out a uh certain uh top end
I will be like okay I have a minimum
that I need to hit but then if I'm doing
squats I'm going until it actually feels
like I'm getting close to failure which
is a lot of volume but you can do it
fairly quickly to ping pong it back to
myself I love the body weight training
gives me a mental break no matter what
modality I'm training in I've trained in
a number over the years weightlifting
power style stuff uh CrossFit kettle
bell sport General bodybuilding
hypertrophy training body weight
training gives me a mental break when
the slog of training starts to wear down
on me right and that does happen and I
think that we as lifters
underestimate how impactful it can be to
take a week not even necessarily as a D
Lo but just to train in a different
modality to remind ourselves we like the
Novelties so that's something I love
about body weight training and I'll even
go on Barb ben.com and look up body
weight training workouts or have someone
just program a bunch of body weight
training for me for a week or two I'm
not really actually Lo sometimes I
actually gain Fitness and strength
believe it or not from that but I'm also
creating a a different thought pattern
and train and I'm reminding myself that
I enjoy training it makes me look
forward to getting back to whatever I
was doing when I need that mental break
I literally was on a trip this past
weekend where I did do some body weight
training in my hotel room and one of the
things that's helpful in terms of
figuring out the programming for that is
I I go back to the fundamental movements
that your body can do you can push you
can pull you can s Squat and you can hip
hinge and so doing uh movements that
encapsulate all four of those movements
it's really helpful to be like okay
that's a full workout I figured out how
to do any type of pulling exercise some
kind of pushing exercise a hip hinge of
some kind and a squat for the most part
if you Encompass all of those movements
you get a full workout and it feels good
I got a sweat on I felt great afterwards
it helps me stay in tune with where I
have I have like hiccups in my Mobility
if that makes sense so like when I'm
when I'm doing like my body weight
squats and stuff I'm like o my ankle
does not feel as the way on my right as
it does on my left or like my my knees
or something like that so it helps me
stay in touch with like making sure that
I'm stretching properly that I'm taking
care of my Mobility training stuff like
that to to not get injured essentially
it helps me stay in tune with my body
and I want to point out body weight
training can take a lot of different
forms uh calisthenics which we've most
mostly been talking about more advanced
gymnastics it's a great way to learn new
skills right work up till plch or
something like that learn strict muscle
ups I mean these are things you can work
toward they're nice goals yoga pilates
pilates I know oftentimes you're using a
reformer but I would put those under a
form of body weight training more
mobility and core uh dominated and
biased all right
Phil I hate tracking macros I hate it I
hate it same same you and me both you
both when Phil and I shared an office
we're remote now and we shared an office
I used to come into the office and for
lunch I would eat a full rotisserie
chicken with hot sauce and like an apple
that was like my lunch and Phil didn't
judge me lots of other people did but I
hate tracking macros my macro tracking
was one chicken that was it that was my
macro tracking but there's one
macronutrient I've taught myself to love
to track Phil do you have a guess what
it is uh I'm gonna guess it is not carbs
not carbs not carbs nailed it nailed it
I am too good at this
game what else you got you can we narrow
it down even further I I'm going to
narrow it down further I got to say it's
it feels like this is a straightforward
layup and I'm going to lay it right up
and say that it is protein David to it's
protein David to protein David to listen
we have a great article we Linked In the
description below and a card probably
like here by former Barb and nutrition
editor Nick English who knows a thing or
two about
macronutrients look the old protein tip
a gram per pound of body weight it's
probably not true and it's almost
certainly not specifically optimal for
everybody right we're all individuals
we're all unique beautiful
snowflakes but I love
that that article still
emphasizes that protein's really
important and it's very easy for us to
not get enough part of that reason is
because protein is like the most
expensive and hardest to get
macronutrient and quality processed food
is all based around easy fats and carbs
right it's easy to get fats and carbs
it's hard to get quality complete
proteins at at scale right and so the
reason I say I tell people and I'm
saying it right now if you hate tracking
macronutrients still fill track protein
is because it's the hardest one to get
the others are easy to come by in just a
general Western diet protein you really
got to prioritize and if you start with
protein if you ba base every meal around
quality protein other things start to
fall into place Phil I know you got some
examples about how tough it is to get
protein yeah so like you said it's a lot
easier to get fat and carbs anywhere
those things taste good they're cheap
and they're available I personally also
hate tracking macros when I was tracking
macros trying to uh slim down what I
found was I it became when I would look
at a meal all I was thinking about was
the numbers and now all of a sudden I'm
developing a negative relationship to
food and that made it impossible to
sustain it was just so difficult but
when you move over and you just track
your protein where you just hit your
protein Target for the day uh that also
helps me with my meal prepping because
what I'll do is I won't necessarily meal
prep everything I will only meal prep my
protein to ensure that I hit my numbers
because it's way easier wherever you are
to find carbs or to find fat like that
stuff you can fill in the gaps based on
how you're feeling and what you're in
the mood for but like as long as you
know that you have your protein set it
makes everything way easier and then
also feels like you have more freedom
within your diet while still managing to
hit your your Macros to like a the
general range that you're looking for by
the end of the week I love that tip if
you're gonna if you if you don't want to
do anything else just meal prep your
protein and then fill in the gaps grze
to fill in the gaps absolutely love that
fill well let's talk about the third
component third component again these
aren't resolutions we're not saying you
got to resolve and publicly post on the
Twitter Instagram X whatever it is that
you're doing these although make a Tik
Tok vid we'll watch it send it to us but
the third component here is something
I've personally struggled with quite a
bit it which is sleep and Phil I've
actually over the years talked to you
about how much I've struggled with sleep
I've mentioned it when we've been on the
road together I've mentioned it I've
mentioned it just kind of in passing
you've even been like hey man you're
looking a little down today what's going
on because I am someone who's always
struggled with sleep hygiene I'm not one
of those people who falls asleep very
quickly Phil I know we've talked about
some of these but what are some things
to keep in mind when it comes to sleep's
impact on performance
specifically muscle growth and
maintenance I think sleep might be the
most
underrated uh Improvement technique for
your gains in training one of the things
that always comes to mind for me five
times fittest man on Earth Matt Frasier
said it best he said if every athlete
could just take a pill like for sleep
and water like if there was just a a
supplement of sleep and water that they
could take everyone would take it
because it would feel like cheating
that's how important that's how
important sleep is and how detrimental
it is if you actually can't maximize it
in a way that's like effective for what
you do day-to- day and I'm similar to
you I I have I'm not one of the kinds of
people that can like hit the pillow and
fall asleep I think that's a superpower
everybody is like uh if there's ever the
time where it's like what would your if
you had a superpower what would it be
people like oh I'd love to be able to
fly or you know become invisible I'm
like I want to be able to control when I
fall asleep that would be amazing and
that would be that would be the
GameChanger for so many so many things I
mean any look look at any research of
the past 50 years everything suggests
that if you improve your sleep every
other modality in your training every
other part of your Waking Life is Just
fundamentally improved by better sleep
more consistent sleep getting that
recover in 75% for most people of growth
hormone is produced during sleep if
that's not a stat that gets you to pay
attention I don't know what is Phil
let's ping pong back and forth give the
folks some sleep hygiene tips two very
important things uh when you go to sleep
two benefits you can have make sure it's
dark make sure it's cold you sleep
better when it is very dark light will
affect your sleep and you will sleep
better when it's cold if you're sleeping
in a very hot environment that's not
going to to lead to better sleep you
want to be somewhere in the low 60s
range I get that that sounds pretty cold
but like if you can get to 62 64 66
degrees in that range that's going to be
more optimal for your sleep than
sleeping in like 76 78 where it's really
hot because then your body will act will
have to like calibrate for that while
you sleep and you will feel drained when
you wake up if you've ever felt sweaty
and depleted when you wake up it's
probably because it was too hot when it
comes to sleeping in a dark place eye
masks I'm a big big fan of wearing eye
masks I know it seems really like
something your grandma would do or
Grandpa would do I love it kind of a
game changer for me one thing I really
like avoiding caffeine before bed I know
that seems really like obvious but like
avoiding caffeine after 5:00 p.m for me
I go to bed around like 11: p.m 11:30
p.m. I kind of wish it was a little
earlier I avoid I hard cut off hard stop
on caffeine at 5:00 pm and really most
days hard stop on caffeine at 2 p.m. so
caffeine has a halflife it does stay in
your system it does impact your ability
to to fall asleep and get restful sleep
so it's not just like oh stop it you
know right before bed stop it hours and
hours before bed honestly if you can
make sure you don't have any caffeine 10
hours before bed that's probably what
you that's probably more optimal for me
absolutely nothing with caffeine after
5:00 P p.m. if I'm going to bed at like
1100 11:30 p.m. but really ideally
nothing after like 1 or 2 p.m. yeah it's
it's tough to say no to that Coke Zero
I'm a man who loves me a good cappuccino
but you got you got to you to keep it
out of your system if you want to get
some good sleep I have found uh
something that's also pretty useful if
you ever are struggling falling asleep
something that has worked for me in the
past especially if my mind is racing or
if I'm thinking about different things
about the day that passed or the days to
come focusing on something that uh calms
your mind down so typically what I'll do
if my mind is racing I'll do something
like consciously think about my
breathing and I will count my breaths to
give my mind a task that is a sort of a
Placid task to just keep my mind from
veering into a space where I'm now
thinking about things that are keeping
me up that are stimulating thoughts uh
and that helps me relax and fall asleep
so if meditation is essentially what
that is like or some variation of
meditation and that can be helpful as
well even before I fall asleep I'll
start dimming my lights before bed uh
and I've started to read before bed I am
not someone who ever really enjoyed that
especially as a kid I know some people
like that but putting your body into a
more relaxed State look screen time
before bed it's bad screen time is bad
if you can shift that to reading before
bed you're you're doing something I get
bored very easily so I want to be doing
something dimming the lights a bit
moving to a physical page like reading
physical books definitely something that
helps me get myself in a more calm and
relaxed State there is also some
research that suggests stretching for 5
to 10 minutes before bed like not
intense yoga right but like very gentle
stretches and there are some good
routines you can find online about this
helps put your body in a more
parasympathetic State your nervous
system in a more parasympathetic nervous
state which could help
you achieve better sleep faster right so
some light stretching before bed um not
vigorous activity but light stretching
in addition to like dimming lights
staying away from screens as much as
possible that could also help you ease
into more restful sleep a general idea
of that as well is if you sit for a lot
of the day and then you go to bed uh
what will typically happen is you might
feel uncomfortable because the your
blood is pulled in your legs if you've
been sitting for a long time so getting
a little bit of blood flow uh at the end
through light stretching or a little bit
of yoga like that can help uh balance
that out before you're laying down and
that can also make it so you're more
comfortable when you sleep and not feel
like you know you're you're tussling and
turning as your body's readjusting
avoiding heavy Foods before bed I uh
personally uh avoid Foods about two
starting about two hours before bed
there's some research that suggests that
can be beneficial for Sleep uh
personally also and again this is not
medical advice I like to make sure uh
I'm supplementing a little extra
magnesium in my diet right um that's
something that I think I I commonly come
in uh under when it comes to daily
consumption and I think a lot of a lot
of folks do so I supplement with a
little bit of magnesium not going to
recommend a particular supplement here
but that has helped me get more relaxing
restful sleep especially in days or
nights after uh difficult training
sessions so that kind of helps me get a
little bit more calm and get a little
bit more relaxed uh and basically
achieve better more restful sleep
throughout the night
magnesium yeah can also conf confirm
that avoiding heavy foods for many a
years in my adolescence I just ate a
gigantic chocolate ganach cake every
single night before bed and I had the
worst sleep in my life so can confirm if
you want to stay stay away from the
heavy food stay away from the cake David
uh I'm also being fous I didn't eat a
chocolate ganache cake let's be real it
was only
Funfetti that's there there's a lot
there there's a lot to unpack and that
might be on a different recording and I
am not a licensed therapist so I can't
really give Phil the uh the full
listening ear he needs on that one look
folks sleep is important it's worth
investing in it's worth prioritizing and
it's worth building your evenings around
that's the last thing I'll say but look
these are just things that we like to
prioritize and we wanted to share and
that we think all strength athletes can
benefit from and the research suggests
it's true there you have it 2024 I
resolve well I can't believe I'm saying
that to do more body weight
training to more closely track my
protein intake and to improve my sleep
hygiene those are three things I'm
saying for 2024 Phil Blackman I do hope
you join me in those and for everyone
watching at home we hope you join as
well but until then it's been a kickoff
New Year episode of strength weekly
we'll be back with regularly scheduled
programming and news next week hope you
all enjoyed the holidays Phil as always
it's a pleasure and honor sir pleasure
and honor
[Music]
sir